admitting everybody on in. Uh so we'll
give everybody a moment.
Good afternoon everybody. Uh I'm Dominic
Zerlo. I am the director for the center
for medical cannabis and psilocybin at
the department of health and this is the
training and education committee meeting
for the medical psilocybin advisory
board. and Brenda Burgard is the chair.
And um uh with that, I'll turn it on
over to Brenda for any opening comments.
Oh, before I do though, just as a
reminder, um we do um ask that people
remember during the course of the
meeting to keep language as appropriate
as possible because um if there is
inappropriate language, we do have to go
through and bleep it out and that make
means it takes longer for us to get
things posted um onto the website. and
we do want to post this and so we just
want to make sure to remind everyone to
use appropriate language so that we can
ensure we can post it as quickly as
possible. And with that, I'll turn it on
over to you Brenda for the the rest of
the intros.
>> Okay. Well, thank you um Dominic and
everyone here today. I'm Brenda Burgard.
I am an LPCC art therapist and also have
a license for addiction. And so, um,
during the comments it when we, um, call
on you, yeah, state your name and and
who you are and all that, but we're
going to, um, skip a lot of the
introductions. So, we'll go over that
once we are, um, taking questions, uh,
for, um, this draft. So, um, Jorge,
you're on. Can you bring up the draft
that we need to go through?
Actually, I'll be taking care of that.
>> Oh, okay. Jorge's got a little little
break today. Okay. Terrific.
>> Yes. Jorge gets a break. I get to uh to
to drive the shared document. Um and
I'll also be putting it into the um the
chat as we go. So, just as we go through
this, I'll be doing it section by
section. So, please just give me a
moment once we get to a new section to
get it into the chat as well. So,
>> okay. Um, do you want me to read or do
you want to read or we could take turns?
>> I'll go ahead Brenda because some of
this as we go through and what I think
everybody will start to see well let me
take a step back a little bit. Um so
first as we did in the last meeting
these are um the drafts that we have for
potential recommendations currently with
regard to educational programs and um uh
and with regard to providers to be able
to go through and what this draft
actually includes is it does include
both requirements and applications. So
as we go through certain parts of it I
just want everybody to keep in mind the
language is not exact. So for example,
we have some places where we may refer
to uh like for example an educational
program. Some places it may be
psilocybin educational program. We're
going through and cleaning that up as
we're actually working on drafting the
final regulations. So don't worry from
those kinds of points. Um please forgive
us for those uh inconsistencies.
Um for example, in some places I think
we refer to some people as permadees
where instead they'll actually be
certified. Um so but again we're go
we're working through to clean that on
up. A lot of this comes from the various
interactions throughout these meetings,
some of the other committee meetings and
also conversations, input and um
information that we've received from a
wide number of community members and
other professionals that are looking at
um this particular field. So um again,
this is the draft as we're moving it
forward. Um, and then we will be working
on um for the hearing, our hope is to be
able to do the hearing or announce the
hearing um in the middle of July to hold
the hearing in August. Um, and so just
to let everybody know that's sort of the
process and the timeline right now. Um,
we did add in a little piece on here
about the locations for for example with
healing centers and that part we are
still working on a bit. Um but um we
wanted to be able to present that if we
have enough time on this. So with that,
I'm just going to dive on in. If people
do have questions as we go, please go on
ahead and put them in the chat. We'll
try to answer them. The one thing I
would ask is um that as we go through,
there are a lot of different sections
and so we may get to something a little
bit later. Um and if that's the case,
we'll make a note and say we'll get to
that in a little bit. So, or at least
I'll try to because I'm going to be
trying to watch the chat as much as I
can and I know the rest of our team is
going to be helping me out with that,
too. So, um, so with that,
>> and [clears throat] Dominic, if you get
tired, let me know because I'll jump in
and, uh, you know, if if we're if we
maybe we could pause, you know, um, in
between some of these and and answer
some of the questions here in the, um,
text. And that's why we'll do it
>> the check
>> section by section. So yeah, absolutely.
Thank you, Brenda. All right. So the
first one is the requirements and items
submitted for the psilocybin educational
program application. And again, by the
way, I'm not going to necessarily read
verbatim um because I do have it in the
chat. We did send it out in advance to
everybody who was registered for today's
meeting as of yesterday afternoon. Um
and we do have it on screen. So most of
these are items that are pretty standard
and it for those who were involved as
far as the producer rules, you'll see a
lot of them are very much the same. So
it includes things such as
organizational chart, proof of
registration with the state of New
Mexico and taxa uh secretary of state
and taxation and revenue, any applicable
New Mexico, city or county business
licenses, certificate of occupancy for
the locations, um and then any
additional documents that we may be
required to ensure compliance with
applicable laws.
um a list of the contact information,
primary contact information.
Um and uh a list of all instructors
including their CV or resumeumés
demonstrating their experience in the
required curriculum areas.
um copy of the syllabi for the courses
utilized within the program and a web
address for where the educational
program will publicly provide updated
syllabi for prospective students. Plans
for record retention, safety and
emergency response plan. Plan for
transparency and disclosure of fees for
students. Plans on how the educational
program will ensure students graduate no
more than two years from the date they
are enrolled. Outline of grievance
procedures for students. consent for
contact information and educational
program websites to be listed publicly
on the department website if approved
and then consent for curriculum and
syllabi to be listed publicly as well.
uh and then provide a third-party
evaluation report of the organization
and the curricula that demonstrates that
it meets the requirements of the pro of
the medical psilocybin educational
program and proof of arrangements with
healing centers or other approved
location for practicum location
placement.
Um there must be a minimum of two
faculty with current practitioner or
facilitator permits from the department
by January 1st of 2027. So that will
give several months for that portion to
be done. Um and I'll just go through
this next um well actually we'll pause
there for a moment. Are there any
questions here on this first section?
>> Okay. Um it looks like Kate Hawk um from
Santa Fe um was up till 2 o'clock last
night and uh she has many questions. Um
so uh will we stand for comments from
Okay. So, she hasn't made a comment uh
yet. So, we don't have anything yet.
>> But I do see Kate has her hand raised.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Kate is
Okay.
>> Go ahead, Kate.
>> Yeah. Hi, everybody. [laughter]
So, I'm looking at this document that um
I just covered with notes before I could
get to sleep last night. Um, and I I
know you all have been working with it
and you've, you know, consulted with
various people. I
still feel like this, you know,
everybody I've talked to who's looked at
this, um, you know, since we got it this
week, um, has questions and concerns.
So, I don't know that in this meeting
um I'm I'm getting ready to fly out of
town right afterwards and I just feel
like boy it everything's been moving so
quickly. I appreciate that in general
and um you know right now I have so many
questions that you know like on this
section for instance well how that uh
you know what about that you know I
don't even feel really coherent
[laughter]
like the third party evaluation
uh people who are are these people are
they going to get paid how does this all
get arranged you know I just have a lot
of questions and there's just one.
>> Sure. And so for example, Kate, there is
an entire section about the third party
evaluation and we've actually brought up
many times and I've brought up quite a
few that you know one of the biggest
issues and concerns is that you know for
having an educational program they need
to be evaluated and so we do have that.
The cost on that is actually on the
educational program. They would have to
pay for that evaluation to occur, but it
does outline here in the document um
what that evaluation should look like
and how that needs to be conducted. So,
>> right, I did I did read that section. I
I went into that into the details. And
there's it's nothing I mean there's some
things that I would say I either don't
understand thoroughly or disagree with.
A lot of it it's like, well, it's
probably okay. But, you know, I just um
feel like the process is going quickly.
And up until this week, um I felt very
confident and um just that's great.
Everything's working out and and now it
just kind of tipped into an overload
point. So, I wanted to speak up.
>> Sure. And I appreciate that, Kate. And
you know, that's a part of why we're
doing this right now. Um, this is not
the only time that these are going to be
reviewed and we're doing this in advance
of the more formalized rule hearing
process. Um, which as I mentioned will
start next month and so there is time
for changes and all of that. This is
looking at the overall um you know uh
how overall this actually is outlined
and is this going to work and how do we
continue to move forward and for example
in the previous set of rule making
that's occurred. We actually did make
changes on that all the way through up
until and including after the rule
hearing. And so this is not the only
time for this. This is the start if that
makes sense.
>> Yeah. Yeah, that does make sense. And
will this will this go to the advisory
board tomorrow?
>> Yes, it will. And again during the
conversations today, you know, changes
may be made because, you know, we do
know people have great comments and they
have great ideas and suggestions and
that's a part of what the idea of doing
this is.
>> Okay. Yeah. And I know there's more
detail later on, but like a list of all
the instructors, I think that's
reasonable. And then you know these
things programs will be developed
continually and opportunities to have
more um instructors
can come up. So I'm just trying to wrap
my head around how is this going to work
in real life.
>> Sure. I understand it is a lot.
>> Yeah. [laughter] I'm sure you appreciate
that.
>> I do. And and just in the interest of
time I I'd like us to continue moving
forward. So if there are specific
questions as we go through and this is
for everybody who's on here, you know,
please don't hesitate. We do want to
answer the questions as best as we can.
So uh next with hand raised is uh Dr.
Fatimi.
Lita go on ahead.
>> Hi it's Lita. I hope everybody is well.
My question is um being specific with it
is about the two faculty with the
current practitioner or uh facilitator
permit from the department by January
1st. How would how are we looking at
implementing that? Is that part of the
reciprocity process that we are we've
been talking about?
>> Yes, it is. And we will cover that in a
little bit of a later section.
>> Okay, great. And then yeah, I I read the
the document a couple of times and I
didn't see any particular Anyways, I
will leave it at that and we'll continue
moving. Uh so we can get to all of it.
Thank you so much.
>> Nope. Thank you.
Okay, any other questions at the moment?
Okay, we'll move on to the next set. So
the next part is just about updates. So
um and again please give me a moment to
get it into the chat but I will have
that there at the beginning of each
section. Um so the updates required is
of course if a program updates their
curriculum they should send submit that
changes in ownership locations practicum
agreements and changes in instructors
and again that's just to ensure that
something does not happen down the road
that would potentially be problematic.
Um any questions on that section?
Okay. And so then the next part is the
approval process. And so the programs
would submit their complete application
packet through and we'll have an
electronic system. So it'll all be done
online. Um save those trees, please. Um
the department will notify uh the
applicant through the system uh if their
application is approved or denied. If
it's approved, it will be effective for
2 years. If it is denied, we'll provide
the notice for the denial. Um, if it is
denied, they may resubmit their
application within 6 months. Um, but an
applicant may not resubmit more than
twice. Um, and applicants may appeal a
denial utilizing the process that we'll
outline a little later in this rule. The
department shall depi shall deny an
application if the submitted curriculum
does not match what is required. Not all
the required items are submitted or are
not complete. the program instructor,
staff, or representatives have made
false or misleading statements to the
department, students, or the public.
Applicants renewing their permit for
being a a program must resubmit the full
packet no more than 60 days and no less
than 30 days prior to the expiration of
their permit. Training programs may
voluntarily relinquish their permit at
any time for any reason. Um,
including sessation of student
enrollment or instructure instruction by
providing written notice to the
department.
Any questions on that?
Okay. So the evaluation
um and this is uh the next section here
um evaluation for the programs. The
department or its designate may perform
remote or on-site assessments of an
approved program uh with or without
prior notice during normal business
hours to determine compliance with the
act and the rule. Assessments may
include a review of the curriculum,
observations, and determine if the
curriculum is uh being implemented with
fidelity. And assessments include review
of the record retention plan and if it
is being followed and any additional
documentation the department may request
to ensure compliance. And then of
course, the department holds the
authority to withdraw approval if the
program no longer meets requirements.
And I do see a couple of questions and
it looks like the first one is Katherine
Warner.
>> Hi everybody. Um I am a licensed
practitioner in Los Cusus. Uh I was also
reading this over last night late. Um,
one thing I'm concerned about, uh, is
this, uh, with or without prior notice
because I'm assuming this also includes,
um,
practicum
education centers and if we're in the
middle of a dosing session, uh, we
cannot have people outsiders coming in.
That can cause major disruption. So, I
think it needs to be with prior notice.
um unless they know that if they show up
and people are dosing they are turned
away.
>> So what we can do on that Katherine I
completely understand what you're
saying. It's a great point as far as
during the practicum is we can actually
exempt that and that the pra if during
the practicum that there needs to be
noticed um for that but as far as for
the other portions of instruction so the
dactic and all of that that should be
within or without. It's very easy for
individuals to, you know, organize
things if they know that something is
happening. It's more difficult if they
don't know. Does that sound reasonable?
>> Sure. As long Yeah. As long as we make a
accommodations for practicum days. Like
it's okay if it's not a practicum day.
If it's just a u maybe we're just
preparing or something. Yeah. Right.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Okay. And as you can tell, I'm
making that note right now.
Okay. And uh Lita, go on ahead. I see
you're next.
>> Yeah, I'm going to echo the same uh
exact concern during a practicum time.
You know, during, you know, I do mainly
the um didactics part of it for the nine
months. And you know we're going to be
partnering to do the practicum with
others. But during a session like that
would be a big you know malpractice and
an ethical issue and the evaluators you
in my opinion they need to be also
certified to understand the ethics of
this work um before they get to become
an evaluator. Thank you.
>> Thank you Lita. Appreciate it.
Anything else?
Okay, we will go on to the third party
requirement.
Pardon me everybody for the moving
around on the screen. It's just what
happens when not trying to uh copy
everything. Uh okay. And so the third
party evaluators. Now this would be
something that would be done by uh the
actual the um educational program would
need to do this. This by the way is not
an unusual uh request. This is something
that is done fairly consistently and
regularly in other areas including
things such as audits financially things
like that. Um so this is a third party
evaluator would need to consist of a
minimum of three individuals who have
three or more years experience in the
one of the following areas. Psilocybin
therapy practice with a master or
doctoral degree and counseling therapy
social work or related public or
behavioral health field. medical or
research practice with a master or
doctoral degree in medicine, pharmacy,
nursing or a related field. An
educational curriculum development and
evaluation with a master's or doctoral
degree in education, educational
psychology or a related field. The
evaluators must not have any conflict of
interest with the organization and
curriculum being evaluated such as the
evaluators must not have participated in
designing or teaching the curriculum
being evaluated and must not have a
financial interest in the organization.
They must sign a confidentiality and
impartiality agreement and they must
provide a report sent to both the
educational program and the department
which includes at a minimum the
evaluator's experience in each of the
required fields. Their conflict of
interest, confidentiality and partiality
agreement. Evaluations of the
reliability, validity and fidelity of
implementation of the curriculum.
Evaluations of the reliability, valid,
validity, and fidelity of implementation
of the student evaluations of
competency, including tests, exams, and
instruct instructor feedback,
recommendations for improvement,
performance evaluations of faculty, and
evaluation of any reported student
grievances.
Okay. And first person up is uh Ann
Mets. Ann, go on ahead.
Hi everyone, my name is Dr. Ann Mets. Um
I'm an LPCC here in Tal County, but I'm
also licensed in Colorado as a clinical
facilitator and I also direct the
Fluence training um which just in full
disclosure, Flu Fluence is not
interested in pursuing um accreditation
here in New Mexico. And so I don't feel
like I really have a dog in this fight,
but I do think um the idea of a third
party evaluator isn't a bad idea. that's
totally appropriate, but I think the
rules don't really address cost, fee
structure, or potential conflicts of
interest. Um, and I think this is just
setting up a consulting market that
would really incentivize favor favorable
evaluations. Um, and so I would just
really encourage the department to
establish clear fee guidelines and also
strengthen con conflict of interest
provisions. um and maybe have um a sort
of screening process by the department
of of thirdparty evaluators.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Anne. Appreciate that. Uh
Katherine,
Katherine, if you're speaking, we can't
hear you.
Can you hear me now?
>> Yes, there you go.
>> Okay. Yeah, it was delayed for some
reason. Um, I kind of wanted to echo
what um, Ann just discussed, but also
I'm kind of want some understanding. So,
this is not something the department
will do. this is something that you're
that like independent people will be
doing like who's gonna I guess like
monitor the third party evaluators or is
that a thing? I I'm just confused. I'm
not really understanding how this will
look. Um and I am concerned that this
could be something that people are just
going to try to make a lot of money off
of.
So, and since both of you have brought
it up as far as fee structure, the
department is not able to actually uh
impose a fee structure and uh so that's
not something that the department is
able to do. Um however, this is not an
unusual situation as having these kinds
of evaluations. This is actually pretty
standard with regard to this. Um and uh
and it does outline what their
requirements are as far as for what the
evaluators what their experience has to
be and the areas that they do need to
evaluate. Um and again this is a pretty
standard set of evaluation
uh requirements.
>> So this is not something sorry Jendra
not something that the the department
will be like it's not going to be
positions at the department is what I'm
hearing.
>> Correct. That is correct. This is
something that so for example um when
and I do this because a lot of people
who have businesses are very used to it.
So and I know several people here have
businesses is where a third party audit
is required. The requirements for that
is that the company that is that is
being audited does have to actually hire
and pay for that third party and to go
through and um to do the audit on it.
And that's essentially what's happening
here. Except you can think about it as
an audit for the curriculum itself. And
that's a part of why it does actually
require that the evaluators actually
include in the report what their
experience in the required fields are to
ensure that they also are experienced in
being able to do this kind of an
evaluation.
So this is something that's not going
we're not going to be able to be
qualified as a center until there are
people offering the service is what I'm
also hearing
>> as an educational program. This is just
educational programs at this point.
>> Right. So and it and can we use people
from other states? Does it need to be
instate?
>> We we did not limit it to instate only
for the evaluators.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> That's a great question.
Okay. Uh, and Lita, you're next.
>> So, as being the, you know, one of the
more prominent trainingmies
in psychedelics,
this doesn't exist with any other, uh,
current psychedelic training programs.
What usually training programs do is
that they show their um their uh what do
you call it um their robustness if you
will by partnering with institutions
such as becoming a CME approved and
accredited program with their local um
medical school for example which is what
we've done we are CME accredited through
UNM and every single lecture gets um
evaluated and re-evaluated and looked at
and it's it's a lot that we do in order
to make sure we are extremely high
integrity and high fidelity. Um you know
for example the other institution that
offers this is CIS which a lot of people
here are familiar with and that's what
they do. They offer CME through
contracted CE organizations. And so in
the psychedelic training world, that's
what we do. And this is not something
that is common. Um, in the world of the
medical industrial complex, which is a
very moneyoriented complex, and that's
what we call it an industry. This is
common where you have a surveyor come in
and do all kinds of surveys. It creates
a lot of stress both monetarily and
emotionally and psychologically
on the on the on the practice if you
will both the you know a medical
practice whether it be a nursing home
facility an ALF is you know assisted
living facility this creates a lot of
issues for them because they have to
have dedicated personnel who are going
to be coming in they have to pay we have
to pay big fees. You know, I have I'm
also a founder of a hospice, ABQ
hospice. And let me tell you, this makes
me not want to have a hospice. And this
would be a um challenge for me as
someone who really cares about the
spirit of the medicine to do what it's
supposed to be doing. This is this is an
issue um for somebody who is you know
randomly like in medical research with a
master's or doctoral degree in medicine
pharmacy nursing or related field and
may not have any understanding of what a
psychedelic program should or would look
like. The first one cell therapy
practice with a masters I get that they
have more familiarity but then the rest
of it doesn't make any sense except that
this is going to this is going to take
everybody down. who cares about uh
bringing something good to our state.
And I think it really takes away what
the spirit of what we're trying to do
here away, you know, from the community
of New Mexico who's extremely
traumatized. And we have to go back to
why we all got together and pushed the
Silicon Medical Act through. Um that's
[clears throat] all I have. Thank you.
>> Okay. Thank you, Lee. I appreciate it.
Um Ian, you are next.
>> Hi. Yes. So I actually just kind of
wanted to speak in support generally. Um
third party evaluators are quite common
in the healthc care space and it is
necessary in order to ensure that we are
using evidence-based practice and that
um we are following you know guidance
and what is responsible without having
um a conflict of interest. I would like
to remind cuz there seems to be a lot of
concern building um that all of these
qualifications are very highly educated
individuals um who have been in a
related field for a good amount of time.
So it would be very
difficult I think for someone to go
through you know all of social work
school a master's degree um just so that
they could become a consultant is
usually more so that they wanted to help
patients in some way and helping out the
educators by just looking through the
curriculum and saying is this normal or
is this you know completely outside of
the realm Um um some other things like
um
a third party evaluator stops an
education null institution from say uh
working with a brand and saying this
product works better even if there's no
concrete evidence for that. So it also
helps to produce reliability in what is
being taught and ensure that there's no
conflicts of interest just within the
educational institution as a whole. Um,
but thank you for this.
>> And next up is Hanifeha.
>> Hi everyone. Good afternoon.
[clears throat] Um, I I'm holding yes, a
bit of concern and maybe an invitation
to think about these three different
individuals who would be holding this
evaluation process based on the nature
of psychedelic assisted therapy and
care. um because there there is a
cultural resonance um and a cultural
humility and a cultural uh understanding
that I'm just curious which of those
which [clears throat] of those three
individuals would be sort of looking for
that and holding that um because it's
also about you know um the cultural res
the cultural resonance of how curriculum
is delivered the actual delivery of the
curriculum and not just the curriculum
itself. Um, so I just wanted to raise
that. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Heneifeha. And that's
actually a part of the main reason why
there's that fidelity of implementation
included in there as far as how it is
how the curriculum is taught, not just
what's on paper. So, thank you for that.
Um, and Lita, back to you.
>> Thank you so much. And Ian, I I do like
what you're talking about as far as
evaluations go and so forth, but um you
know, we already do that for our CME and
CEU uh approval for every single
session. So then it's a very rigorous uh
thing that we do. Maybe that's what
needed to be needs to be added to this
document in for this requirement of
evaluation period. Each session that we
have has been evaluated by the director
of CME at University of New Mexico
School of Medicine. Mind you, for us um
in months in advance, we have conflict
of interest that is signed by every
single faculty member who presents to
our to our members. And uh I mean it
doesn't get more rigorous than that.
When you have uh you know a lens that's
looking at every single session that has
to be approved. They fill out a conflict
of interest. It's a requirement and if
it doesn't get filled out that session
is not approved for CME or CEU. We have
to have evaluation
um for the session and before the
session starts people have to sign in. I
mean it doesn't get more rigorous than
that. So maybe um maybe that needs to be
added in so that it can be an or there
um for the requirement
um because if if you have other programs
that already are doing the CU work man I
have to tell you we spend about 7 to
$10,000 a month for just operations and
we're not in the green we are almost in
the red and every month just for the
operations And if you guys want to bring
another third party evaluated into the
mix, I don't I don't know. It's just
duplicate work. It's more work for the
for the third party to figure out who's
who. So to me, I think an or would be um
would make sense, especially when you're
going with a, you know, the only states
like university program. I mean, they're
state-of-the-art school of medicine
who's approving every single session um
with that conflict of interest embedded
in it and evaluations per session. Um
yeah, that's my that's my thought there.
Maybe adding it in.
>> Thank you, Lita. Uh next up is Lisa
Ginsburg. Lisa,
>> thank you. I agree with Lita. Um I think
for schools like um Lita just mentioned
including Chunga Institute we approved
like Chunga is approved by the board of
higher education of Oregon
um Colorado
we offer continue educational credits
all these courses have to be approved in
order to issue continue educational
credits it needs to be approved with a
third third party and it's quite
rigorous experience
um and process. Another question uh for
this third I feel like that will make
programs even more expensive because the
programs will not observe the course. PS
will pay for the third party evaluation
which will be in tens of thousands of
dollars considering that it's 150 hour
plus program even 60 hour to go through
the full curriculum by third party it's
quite costly experience we all know that
uh we use professional educational
designers we have person with a masters
in education from Stanford designing our
curriculum
that's expensive now we're going to add
a third party
if we're going to pay for that that cost
will be passed down to the facilitators
through our tuition. So I think it's a
big question that we need to consider if
this programs already offering continue
educational credits and already approved
by some governing bodies like the
commission of higher education. I don't
know if we should add another layer of
third party verification.
Thank you.
Thank you, Lisa. So before we continue
with some of the other comments just
because I am cognizant of the time what
I'm hearing is that we add in an option
with regard to having CME and CE CEU
approval of the curriculum so that if
the um the educational program is able
to show that all of their coursework
also contains CME/CEUS
that that be an alternative to the third
party evaluators.
And if [snorts] we add that on in and we
would do that as an alternative so we
would still have both pathways because
not everybody necessarily is going to be
able to be available for the third
party. Would that be acceptable?
Can I see some thumbs up or I'm seeing
several? Okay. So we will add that on in
and we'll add that in as part of the
recommendation is that we will have an
alternative path utilizing CMEs. So, um,
if if there's additional questions on
other portions, we'll be happy to hear
them. But if it's just about that, um,
if we could go ahead and move on, I
think that would be fine. But, uh, Ian,
additional questions or comments.
>> I just wanted to clarify that I would
agree with that because I only spoke in
opposition, but um, yeah, CME would be a
third party that I would agree with also
evaluating. Thank you. Okay.
And okay, thank you James. I can tell it
was about that. Thank you. See, and this
is why, as we say, that's why we want to
have these conversations because we do
come up and have those additional ideas
in it. So, thank you everybody. Um, the
next set is continuing education
requirements. We did get a question on
this um in uh uh separately uh after
sending out the um the um sorry sending
the document out yesterday. So I'll
answer that at the end. But basically
it's that the diagnostic clinicians
would have to complete a minimum of
eight hours of CMEs and the
practitioners and facilitators and
that's every two years sorry every two
years and practitioners and facilitators
20 hours. um and they would have to keep
current their basic life support CPR uh
in addition to those 20 hours of CEUs.
Um so the question that had come in is
this would this be an addition? So for
example, licensed social worker clinical
social workers have to have so many CMEs
or CEUs over the course of a 2-year
period. Um this would not be an addition
to that. This would be something that as
a part of those if someone is doing that
we just want to ensure that they are
specific CMEs or CEUs for psychedelic
medicine or therapy. So that's just what
that aspect is. It would not be
something that would need to be separate
for individuals who have other lentures.
So if you have to recmp complete a for
example 120 uh cmemes over the course of
two years these could just simply be a
part of those. Uh and then Katherine you
have your hand up.
>> Yes. Um are we done then talking about
what the requirements are to be an
educator?
like is that
>> we had gone over that last time.
>> Um yes, but if you have other questions
on that because there is a little bit a
little later that does touch upon all of
that. Okay.
>> So if you have a question if you want to
bring it up then or
>> I just think that I just think the
educators need to have more than the
minimum requirements that we're
requiring for um facilitator for the
licensing of facilitator and
practitioners. I think that the
educators need like I don't think you
should be training if you've only had 14
experiences. I think I think 14
experiences is a low number to begin
with and I think that the educators need
to demonstrate a higher level of
experience and
>> um then I think just the typical. So I
don't know if that was addressed and I
missed it. I just want to um just make
sure I voice that. I I think I know what
you're talking of talking about,
Katherine, and please correct me if I'm
wrong. What you're saying is there
should be a requirement that the
instructors, so the educators need to
have more experience
>> um than just a standard
uh facilitator practitioner level. Um,
if that's the question, what would be a
recommendation as to how much
>> or how many how much experience?
>> Yeah, I don't have a quick answer. Um,
but just what's coming to my head is
maybe a minimum of like 40 people that
they have um worked with.
And would you say that for all of the
instructors or in this case we have two
have to are required to be
>> practic I think maybe practicum is what
I'm mostly worried about um because
you're right like just giving training
on uh like didactic training I don't
think it needs as rigorous but I guess
I'm more just concerned about practicum
so I don't know how everybody else feels
about that.
>> Yeah. Uh, and I I think you meant 40
unique patients, correct, Katherine?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> And again, uh, we'll work on the
language a little bit. Do we have
disagreements on that or well, uh, I'm
going to put it in here as a placeholder
at the moment. Um, and it looks like we
have some agreement here in the chat as
well, but um, with that, I'll go to
James first and we'll see. Go ahead,
James.
Afternoon,
Dominic, and everyone else. And again,
Brenda, thank you for sharing this. Um,
I just think that we need to be very, we
need to really think about this. Um, uh,
there does need to be some minimums. Um,
and I I think we definitely need to use
that language still minimally. Um, but
but this again, we're talking about a
brand new program with people who how do
we validate,
you know, these people's experiences and
time? That's very important that we
think about that when you're when you're
talking about minimums. And so if we're
trying to say somebody needs a minimum
of 40 patients,
you know, how do we validate that being
such a new program, you know, if you
think about that, that would have to be
pre-existing people who have already
been licensed either in Oregon or
Colorado or other, but technically kind
of those two only because those are two
and only states that technically could
say and come out and say we have data.
Um, if not, it's underground,
truthfully. And so, you know, if that's
that's a blocker that's going to be a
hard stop for a lot of this guys,
because you're not going to have these
programs up and coming with these people
with this much experience. So, you got
to think about that when you guys talk
about minimums and you're talking about
40 and then you're talking about how
many programs there are and then
actually the number of people is very
minimal. And so I just want to caution
that and to be very cautious on when you
talk about minimums in these programs.
I've done programs. I've set up
programs. I'm an educator. And that's
one of the big things. There's not a lot
of people preset or or pre-certified or
pre-registered, pre- anything in this.
So think about that when you guys talk
about minimums. Thank you.
>> Thank you, James and Lita.
>> Thank you. Yeah, you know, I agree with
James. it's tough to really um you know
because we're pioneering this I think um
having particular numbers make it
becomes more difficult and I do see
Katherine's point in if you're going to
instruct somebody
um you do need more experience and more
hours you know I do see a very distinct
difference between someone who's held
what 10 sessions versus someone who's
held a hundred and plus where there's a
maturity and a wisdom that comes with it
and the newer person tends to want to
say hey let's do this everybody and
there's more of a enthusiasm to get
everybody on board where versus the 100
plus you know person and I'm just making
numbers up I'm not saying this is what
it should be um has more of a maturity
of understanding that no this is a
personal journey and people have to come
to this place themselves and they have
to be called to the medicine and so um
yeah it's this is a tough one. I think
we need further discussion on this but I
do agree that there needs to be more if
you're going to instruct
someone or you're going to educate a
population of practitioners.
I mean, in any realm, you would have to
have gone through some years of work
yourself. So, I just leave it at that.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Leave it. Uh Erica, you're
next.
>> Your mic might be off. Sorry, I have to
control shift M and I can't do chat, so
I don't know what's going on there. But
anyway, I'm curious, is the Department
of Health going to limit the number of
educational programs that they approve
within New Mexico?
>> Uh, no, there is no limit.
>> Okay.
>> It will be programs that actually meet
the criteria.
>> Okay. Thanks.
>> Thank you, Erica. Uh, Hanifeha,
>> hello again. um kind of timing in to
what what was being shared that James
was sharing in terms of these limits.
I'm going to be the person bringing this
up um again, but really thinking about
[clears throat]
also people's experience holding
individual care as well as group care
because they're very different. And so
being able to be to teach people and
train people on how to how to hold those
two different models would be very
important and also create another
complexity when it comes to
setting the the the qualifications of
like well how many groups and is it how
many groups how many sessions how many
people so I just wanted to raise the
case for group care with all of this as
well thank you
>> thank you Henha and we do actually have
that portion in the practicum so we'll
be sure if uh depending on what happens
on this particular piece which it sounds
like we'll need more conversation on um
you know then we'll make sure to include
that uh an is next go ahead Yeah,
>> great. Um, I wasn't quite sure when I
should bring this up, but I feel like
since we're talking about the issue of
supervision around practicum, um, I
really have a significant concern about
the supervisory practicum requirements
for practitioners.
Um, the rules that were disseminated at
the last meeting and then also the ones
here require practitioners to complete
20 supervisory practicum hours as a
condition of initial lenture. Um in
behavioral health field supervision
works really differently. Licensed
clinicians work independently for a
period of time and then they may choose
to pursue an optional super supervisor
credential if they want to supervise
trainees or junior staff. Um supervision
is not a licensing requirement for
anyone who's a social worker or
counselor. It's an additional credential
that people opt into and I really think
New Mexico psilocybin rules should
follow this model and not mandate
supervisory training for all
practitioners. Um, more critically,
there is no psilocybin specific
liability insurance product available
that covers clinical supervision of
psilocybin therapy. So for practitioners
with behavioral health licenses,
supervisory liability will not be
covered under their existing behavioral
health liability insurance and requiring
practitioners to complete supervisory
hours without available insurance
coverage creates an uninsurable
liability that will fall outside of any
coverage. And I think um as a point of
professional courtesy, no one should be
required to perform work that they can't
insure. Um, moreover, I think it's
really important that practitioners
should gain confidence, expertise, and
clinical judgment by working
independently in the field before having
to take on supervisory responsibilities.
Um, and I would recommend really that
they consider that you all consider
establishing a practitioner supervisor
credential as an optional designation.
Um, practitioners with secondary
behavioral health licenses should have
the same practicum requirement as other
facilitators without the additional
supervisory requirement. Um, but those
who are interested in supervising could
could pursue the practitioner supervisor
credential after field experience and
ideally after insurance products become
available to cover this work. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Hen. I do appreciate that
except for that the issue there would be
that the facilitators do need to be
supervised by the practitioners based
upon the model that is created and
that's actually why that is there. It's
not necessarily that they are
supervising other practitioners but the
facilitators.
>> I I still think my point stands that if
you're not interested in supervising
facilitators, you shouldn't be required
to have to complete supervisory hours. I
think that should be something that opts
in. If you're only interested in
practicing as a solo practitioner and
you have a behavioral health license, I
think it's um it's unfair to require you
to supervise someone else, particularly
when there's not an insurance product
out there that will allow you to
actually supervise a facilitator. Um I'm
just sort of pointing out that we can't
like force people to do something that
they can't get liability coverage to do.
>> I appreciate it, Ann. Thank you. Uh
James,
>> hey, just one thought I had on this
because I do think that there needs to
be some type of oversight, right? And
what we do and I'm, you know, in the
program I'm in with that stuff is that
um the states that have done this, what
they do is they allow a subject matter
expert. So what happens is the school
itself has to submit the application
with their instructors. So, they're kind
of pre-screened by like the DO. That's
my idea here. So, we would if we were a
school, let's say, uh, with Dr. Lita.
Um, and and she would submit her
instructors to the DO and that those
instructor would would be reviewed by
the DO and then they would kind of give
a green light uh to those instructors
specifically individually. And so, that
the DO could have some oversight on
who's actually qualified. And that's
what they do in Oregon. Again, you have
to review your your application has to
be reviewed not by the OA, but has to be
reviewed by a third party certification
through the state, right? So, they say
that that person's qualified and that
that school then is qualified. So, that
takes away a lot of this. Um, and so I
just thought that might be an idea here
is that we would, you know, be
submitting, you know, our instructors to
the DO for review and approval. And once
approved, those subject matter experts
um and that would be the application
process that you guys would create would
just be like here's our qualifications
to be an instructor. And then when we
had a school, we would submit that
application based off of your
requirements. Very simple. So just a
thought. Thanks.
>> Thank you, James. I appreciate it.
Okay. Any other comments at this time?
Okay. Um
so uh the next set sorry I'm scrolling
back on down my apologies everyone is on
the reciprocity. Now while we have
covered portions of this before I just
wanted to bring this on up because we
did add in um because we had had some
discussion but hadn't presented all of
the details on it. But just to go
through this is uh the reciprocity piece
is this essentially is that so that
people who have gone through other
trainings at this time would be able to
uh practice here in New Mexico. And so
they would be able to to be permitted as
a practitioner or facilitator if they
are able to do the following. Provide
documentation of completion of the
government approved psilocybin
educational program from another
jurisdiction. complete the New Mexico
module. Uh complete the required
practicum or demonstrate completion of a
practicum or practice with the minimum
number of patients and hours is required
in New Mexico. or if some of the
practicum hours have been completed in
another jurisdiction and are not able to
be verified by the department, the
remaining practicum hours required in
New Mexico may be completed through the
New Mexico approved program so long as
the total hours and minimum number of
patients required are met. For the
practitioner permit, the reciprocal
applicant will need to ensure they
complete the 20 supervisory practicum
hours in New Mexico. The exceptions for
this any reciprocal applications
received by the department by December
31st, 2026 will not be required to
complete the full practicum hours
required, but must demonstrate
completion of at least 40 hours of
contact time with a minimum of two
separate individual sessions or two
separate group sessions for preparation,
administration, and integrative therapy
with treatment. The other exception is
that the department reserves the ability
to wave, temporarily suspend, or reduce
any of these rules regarding the
practicum for individuals applying up
until December 31st, 2027 in order to
facilitate the permitting of individuals
trained by other approved programs to
build the initial infrastructure of the
program.
I I'm going to pause there for a moment
on this section
on that. Um, and that is correct. They
do have to show that they do have at
least 40 contact hours with patients.
Sorry, uh, for those who don't see the
chat, uh, Ann had asked if it meant that
applicants prior to the end of this year
would not have to complete the, um, the
supervisory practicum.
Okay. Uh so the next step is uh for
another government approved psilocybin
educational program to be accepted they
would need to do the following
documentation that the psilocybin
educational program has been approved by
another governmental governmental agency
or authority by either that they are on
the list that the department has already
approved for reciprocal psilocybin
educational programs from other
jurisdictions
or provide the following documentation.
Proof the program has been approved by a
government entity or government entity
provide their educational program
curriculum and a curriculum equivalency
for the dactic portion when compared to
the required New Mexico education
program. Department approval of
reciprocity of reciprocal psilocybin
educational programs is valid for two
years from the date of approval and that
uh reciprocal psilocybin educational
programs may request a curriculum review
30 days prior to their expiration and
after review by the department their
approval renewed for two more years.
Individuals applying for reciprocity and
having completed another governmental
approved program outside of New Mexico
and verified by the department will be
accepted from the practicum hours if
they apply for reciprocity by December
31st, 2026.
One note on it um on this is the part
where the list of department approved
programs we have already stated and
would include on that list programs that
already are approved by the states of
Colorado and Oregon because they're
already documented and we have that
information. So they would already be
automatically on that list. Um so uh
first person is Lita. Thank you Lita. Go
ahead.
Thank you. Yeah, I have a question, you
know, regarding the ones who are
pioneering their own programs in our uh
state. Um that doesn't fit under the
reciprocity portion and I'm wondering if
there's another section for that
submission
um of the program and I'm just going to
Yeah, I wonder
>> there is not at this time, Lita. It
would need to be they would need to be
approved by the department.
>> Gotcha. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Or or again as I know another
governmental entity.
So if there's already an approval from
another governmental entity that could
be submitted as well.
>> Okay. A governmental entity such as Can
you give me an example other than the
DO?
Uh well uh the um in DO it would be um
Department of Higher Education
um or some other governmental entity uh
or like uh different
>> you know different jurisdictions have
different names for them or and things
like that. So you know or even quite
frankly if it was the federal department
of education.
>> Does that make sense?
>> Yes. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Uh and next an
Hi, sorry this is um just a quick
question earlier on the document it says
but people need to complete 40 hours of
contact um are are somehow do that and
then the last bullet point seems like
people are exempted from practicum and
so I'm just sort of curious are people
required to complete a training program
or are they required to complete a
training program and have the 40-hour
practicum
>> thank you an that's actually just uh
some of the clarity that I was talking
about earlier. They still need to show
the 40 hours that they have that 40
hours, but they would be otherwise
exempted from the practicum, the 40
contact hours. Does that make sense?
>> That does make sense.
>> And let me put that in. Uh I'll just
make a note to add to clarify that part
here. Thank you. I appreciate the catch.
[laughter]
Uh Chris to answer that. I don't know uh
if Nuropa is has been approved
previously, so I do not have an answer
for that off the top of my head. We
would have to get the information from
them.
I have a question, Dominic. Do we are we
getting close to finding out uh which
institutions or education programs have
been decided by DO yet? Uh the only ones
that we've discussed are the ones that
have already been approved by Colorado
or Oregon. And we actually disseminated
that list at the last meeting I believe
or prior to the last meeting.
>> Oh yeah.
But we can if necessary we can always
send it out again.
Okay, thank you everybody. Uh, and I see
there's actually some comment about
Nuropa in the um in the chat. So, uh,
sounds like that. Well, I'm not sure at
this point. We'd have to look into that
a little bit more either way.
Um, and then the next part that we have
is, uh, testing out of the dactic
portion because one of the things that
we have talked about quite extensively
in various meetings has actually been
about people who have experience and
that have been doing this for many years
and have the knowledge and the
understanding. So, we did want to ensure
that there was a testing out possibility
for the dactic portion. And with that,
um, uh, well, I'll just read through it.
So, the approved programs must offer an
option for a student to take the test
for each module without attending
lessons or classes except for the New
Mexico module. Everybody has to take the
New Mexico module, which if you missed
it in some of the probably hundred other
times I've said it in different
meetings, that is going to be created by
the Department of Health and offered
free of charge. Um, the cost to take the
test for each module cannot be more than
1/4 of the normal price of each of the
educational modules. If the student
receives a passing grade for the module
test, then they will be if considered to
have completed the module. If they do
not then they will not have completed
the module and the educational program
may allow students to retake the test
without attending the lessons at their
discretion. So it will be that the
choice of the program the educational
program students who utilize this option
must still complete all other
requirements for the educational program
including the New Mexico module any
certifications simulated patient and
practicum requirements to graduate from
their program. Any
questions?
>> Lita, go ahead.
>> I guess I have more of like a
conversation around this. Um, I'm trying
to uh put it as, you know, like an
implementation into our program as an
example. Um, and I'm trying to figure
out how that would
um, how this like pans out on the
ground, you know, because oftentimes,
you know, I was a policy maker at UNM
Health, you know, sciences center, the
entire thing. And I remember as policy
makers, you know, people would make
policies and we talk about it, but then
when implementation on the ground is
happening, you're like, whoa, this is
very, you know, does not fit at all the,
you know, what's happening. And so I'm
trying to figure out so um are we
talking about if a student um can you
just give me an example? Maybe that's
that would be
>> sure helpful. Thank you.
>> Sure. So say for example we have
somebody who has been practicing
um in Colorado for example but they did
not go through an approved program. That
program that they did go through is now
out of business. So they can't get
records or anything else. And instead of
them needing to necessarily go through
all of the didactic portion of the
training, they would then be able to
test out um or have the option to test
out. So that's really what that's for.
It also could work for individuals who
have been um practicing underground or
previous to the act where uh again they
may have gotten a lot of experience and
have a lot of knowledge and
understanding and that by being able to
do this it would help them to um to be
able to be a part of this. you know, in
that sense of we want to acknowledge
that experience and all of that, but at
the same time, we still need to ensure
that that experience is actually there.
Um, and we want to make sure that
there's not, you know, a I hate to say
it this way because I always like, as
many of you know, like to think the best
of everybody, but to ensure that there's
not a bad actor, for example.
>> Yeah. Thank you so much for that
explanation. That makes a lot of sense.
Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
Okay, I don't see any other questions.
So, we'll move on. So, this next set is
about uh the application process. Um and
uh so give me just a moment to put it in
the chat. Um and so for this um this
would just be and this is for the
different certifications for the
diagnostic clinician, practitioner and
facilitator. And uh this is the part uh
within this we have um we had already
gone through many of the requirements
but so essentially the applicant must
complete submit a completed application
packet through the electronic system. So
everything will be online um and the
department will notify the applicant on
whether or not they have been approved
or if they are denied and if approved
it'll be valid for two years. The uh
application can be resubmitted within 6
months but may not be submit more than
twice. Um oh and I apologize everyone
that should have been more than twice in
a six-month period
that got edited out at some point. So my
apologies to everybody. Um, the reason
for that, just so everybody knows, um,
and I believe that was in the earlier
portion, and I missed that as well now
that I think about it, but, um, what the
six-month period and the reason why not
submitting more than twice is we don't
want somebody who, you know, for
example, left off their date of birth
and so resubmits it and is essentially
utilizing the department to turn around
and say, "We're going to just keep
submitting applications until we finally
get it right." And that they haven't
actually completed it each time. And so
that's why this is just really there to
say please complete your application. We
do understand mistakes happen so you can
resubmit it, but don't just keep
submitting it to us for us to proofread
if that makes sense. Um, and I say that
because that did happen to us early on
in the cannabis program where we did not
have that limitation. So that's all that
actually is. Um, and then of course
applicants may appeal a denial utilizing
the process outlined in this rule and
we'll have that later on in the
document. Uh the department shall deny
an application if not all the required
items have been submitted or completed.
Um insufficient or expired lensure,
missing or inadequate documentation of
certification, education or practice
requirements. The applicant has made
false or misleading statements in the
application or to the department or the
public. And for renewal, applicants must
complete the application no more than 60
days and not less than 30 days prior to
the expiration of their permit. And then
uh they may voluntarily relinquish the
permit at any time um by providing
written notice and then consent to
having contact information with their
name, phone number, and email address
published uh publicly. Um
so at this point, any questions?
Okay. So the next set
uh is
now in the chat.
So this is for the reciprocal or
facilitator application and submit a
completed application packet. Um, and
that'll include having completed the
psilocybin educational program from
another jurisdiction. Provide the
documentation that it is approved by
another governmental agency or authority
by either that they're already included
in the department approved list. Um, and
if not, that they provide the
documentation of that approval and the
curriculum equivalency. And that's just
very similar to the requirements we had
up above. Uh and then documentation of
active practitioner or facilitator or
equivalent lensure or permit in another
jurisdiction. Documentation of minimum
core practicum hours and New Mexico
practicum hours as outlined above.
Documentation of completed the New
Mexico specific module. Verification of
current BLS certification. Documentation
of current HIPPA certification W9. an
att testation they are not a registered
sex offender and that the department
will deny or revoke a permit to anyone
who is a registered sex offender and
personnel data as appropriate. Date of
birth, New Mexico driver's license,
phone, email, legal name and affirmation
and consent. And I do have to apologize.
I think we are missing that part um here
in the application process for all of
these that same information that's down
here. It just we uh accidentally it
looks like I did not copy it over uh
that other information um as far as from
the New Mexico specific training module
or I'm sorry the verification of BLS and
below are actually a part of the regular
application as well. So, my my um my
apologies everyone that again when we
were creating the full document that
just got deleted off somehow, but that's
duplicated there. Um and for those who
are interested as far as why we would
need a W9, just to outline that portion
real quick, the main reason is when we
get to the point with the um equity fund
and the reimbursement on that, that
reimbursement will need to go to the
various providers directly. And so to be
able to do that, people need to be
registered in the uh state share system,
which is the financial accounting
system. And to do that, we need a W9.
And so we're just shortcutting that
process by requiring it with the
application.
Uh and then Katherine, go on ahead.
There you go. It wouldn't let me unmute.
I remember I think it was last time
Chris had mentioned a VLS certification
being maybe a bit of a higher level than
we need. I wasn't sure if that got
fleshed out or not. Is that what we're
going with? Um
>> we Yes, that's a great question,
Katherine. We did look at that and we
did determine that the BLS was actually
the appropriate level. We do know that
when things all go well, it may seem
like a little bit of um you know, a
little too much and not necessarily
needed, but there have been times where
that training has been necessary. I know
when I've gone through it myself, I
never thought I'd be in some of those
situations that I would be in my work
and yet was. And so, it's more from a
precautionary standpoint. We did look at
doing it as a requirement for uh just
doing CPR, which is I think what Chris
Oh, and Chris just raised his hand, so
we'll we'll check in with him here in a
moment.
>> But um it was something that we did look
at and did decide that yes, in many
cases it may seem like it's a little
much, but this is about that safety
issue and and trying to ensure on that.
So, um Chris, go on ahead.
Um, yeah, I'm just curious on that
because it it's really essentially the
same thing except for in BLS you use
BVMs, which the bag valve mask requires
two people to be actively doing CPR to
actually work and you have to have them.
So, if we're not going to require that
equipment, I think we'll actually be
doing people a disservice. And you know,
if there's less than two providers in
the room, then you can only use a mask
anyway. You can't use a BVM. Um, and so
again, it's it doesn't it seems seems
odd is all I'm saying.
>> So, so Chris, we actually are going to
be requiring that mask and there do have
to be at least two providers in the room
at all times
>> except of course emergencies. Even if
you have two, one of them's probably
going to be on the phone with 911, so
you're still not using a BVM. Just
things to consider, like it's probably
uh and and they don't train as hard as
normal CPR, you know, with just a mask
um as thoroughly in BLS. So,
I I'm not opposed to it. I just
consider.
>> Yeah, these are considerations that I
think you guys should take into account
because it really doesn't make sense
from my vantage point and I taught first
aid and CPR for years and I'm recently
certified in BLS and it just doesn't
make sense honestly.
>> Okay, thank you Chris. I appreciate it.
Okay, any other questions?
Okay.
Uh and so uh patient application and
record. Um and again part of this has to
do and and really will come through with
regard to um when we really start having
the research components
but also just because we do need to um
to record and ensure that uh the records
are there. And because somebody may uh
this makes it a little bit easier for
example with a diagnostic clinician if
they have certified a patient then that
can actually move to a variety of
practitioners and facilitators. Um but
so the patient application again it
would be done through electronic uh
situation online document the diagnosis
by the clinician. So the clinician would
do that aspect and then it would just
have basic personal data of date of
birth, phone, email, mailing address, so
contact information, legal name and
their affirmation and consent forms. The
diagnostic clinician, practitioner, and
facilitators would then record the
diagnosis qualifying the patient, their
attestations about evaluating and
treating the patient, the date and type
of service for evaluation, preparatory
session administration, including what
the approved location. Uh the unique
identification number of medicine for
those who may recall that uh all of the
medication will actually be tracked and
have identification numbers and that's
what that is. and then the dosage
utilized. Um, and then of course the
next one would be the integrative
therapy session. And as we've discussed
in many many situations, any adverse
events and just to note, we're not just
talking about what happens on the day of
administration. It also can be after the
fact on that. Um, and then the
information once we have that uh with
that'll be required for equity and
access fund purposes. Um, we just don't
have that information yet. That's part
of the next set of rules. So, uh, and
any questions on this? Oh, yes, Lita, go
ahead.
>> So, question that I have is based on the
diagnos permitted diagnosing clinician.
you know, majority of our well, first of
all, you know, because of our
malpractice laws in New Mexico, uh, the
past few years, I know this legislative
session tried to reconcile some of those
issues with malpractice laws, but pri
prior to that, in 12 months, 300
physicians left the state of New Mexico,
which created a huge issue in care
delivery. patients on are on waiting
list like six to nine months and prior
to that it was still we're still
underserved uh from a ratio standpoint
of patient to doctor and so if we are
talking about a permitted diagnosing
clinician
I'm wondering what exactly we mean by
that um and if it is a physician or an
NP or PA um you know that would be This
is a huge issue uh for an access
standpoint. It's a huge bottleneck that
will I mean the only you know clinician
I know of is me in the state of New
Mexico who would be you know I don't
have the panel size to even take 10 more
patients for example to just give them
the diagnosis so that they can enter the
program. I think that is a it would be a
flaw in the system and the
implementation of it onto the ground. I
think a better model would be if an
individual which we do through you know
multitude of physicians that we have in
our state to give the diagnosis within
the four diagnoses that we have as
stated by the bill of treatment
resistant depression. People get
diagnosed by that every day in our
community. PTSD, you know, primary care
physicians are diagnosing that every day
in in patients. Um, addiction, any
addiction center, any addiction, you
know, practitioner can't obviously has
that diagnosis already. Um, and that
diagnosis doesn't have to come uh by a
diagnosing clinician. Um if a patient
already has that diagnosis ba you know
by their uh provider physician NP or PA
already in a system to me if they're
able to provide that to their care team
the psychedelic care team the psilocybin
care team that should be able to qualify
them to as an entry point and not create
that very tiny bottleneck. for them to
have to be um
approved by a diagnosing physician. I
don't know if that that is making sense
or not, but I'd love to hear your your
thoughts on it.
>> Thank you, Lita. It it does make sense.
However, it there's actually two pieces
to it. One, it's also the evaluation and
ensuring that the medical evaluation
that psilocybin would be an appropriate
treatment for someone. And so it's not
just about receiving that diagnosis, but
also ensuring that the psilocybin would
be potentially more beneficial than
potentially harmful for the patient and
ensuring that that aspect is covered
from a medical side. And so that's a
part of the reason for that. and um and
and that's actually been made very clear
to us um through several conversations
and aspects of it that there has to be
that medical aspect of it at some point
through the process. And so I know that
in some other situations what's been
suggested is that the patient go for
example to the practitioner so the
therapist whichever provider is going to
be doing that but then if they have not
yet gotten that medical clearance they
would then have to go to receive that
and then come back and so that actually
would create even more of a bottleneck
in that regard. Um does it mean that
when the program first starts that we're
going to have a lot of providers? No,
not necessarily. And it will take time
to develop, but remember that's a part
of building that infrastructure. And we
don't anticipate with the December 2026
that there's suddenly going to be
hundreds of providers available. That's
going to build up over time. We did
experience the same exact situation, for
example, with medical cannabis. And when
it first started, there were only a few
providers who would do it for a variety
of reasons, including stigma issues,
which we need to educate quite a bit on.
including other uh you know as far as uh
just even patients finding providers.
It's a part of why we're asking to for
the contact information to be made
available. Um various other aspects as
well but we now have had over well
several thousand providers who now have
actually referred patients and
recommended patients into that program.
So it takes time to build up. You are
correct. right off the off the bat there
will not be very many providers. Um but
it will and it will take time for that
to build but that is a part of that
buildup. We've never said and we
continually say that when the program
first launches when we see those first
patients it will take time to build. Um
and so that's a part of that aspect. So
we do understand that part. Um and and
we've stated many of this much of this
many other times before as well.
>> Yeah. And you know the other
Sure. And you know it just I I don't see
us being able to um to help our
community the way we have imagined.
um because if if it's only the
diagnostic clinician who is um taking
those patients I I mean again you know
in our community I don't know any
any um other physicians for example who
would be also taking the risk you know
of um having a DEA license and I know
we're talking about having a controlled
substance
um uh license but that's against federal
law. Um, and so
I see this as a major issue moving
forward um, in our community
unfortunately. And I and I understand I
I understand that there has been
discussion about it and I thank you for
bringing that forward. Um, and maybe we
weren't paying as much attention to it,
including myself, but now that I'm
looking at it, there's no I I don't know
how um we'll implement. I mean, we'll I
don't know. I don't unless we expedite
the, you know, the portion.
Maybe there are physicians in the
community who are interested. I know
many physicians are very fear driven
especially because they have a DA
license and this is a substance um
schedule you know uh it's a schedule one
substance
um and so making it more palatable for
them to want to participate in the
program that's a hurdle that I see every
day um in physicians and in practices
um and to
to you know help our community. I see
that as as a blockage. Um but yeah, you
know, take it for for what it what it
is. I don't I don't know how uh this is
going to pan out um or how long it will
take to educate um the diagnosing
physicians to even you know evaluate the
interest cuz many I I'm connected with
many physicians in our community and and
a lot of them get scared even just
talking about it. They're like, "Oh, is
this legal to talk about um because of
their DA license and control substance
um license?" And so, just food for
thought,
>> and it definitely is, Lita, and we do do
hear that. Um and and I do understand,
and we did experience the exact same
thing with cannabis. I had many many
providers at that time who were
constantly saying no I can't do this
because of DEA license stigma issues
lots of other things. So that education
is a key part of it. The other thing
just to give you as an idea is we had
two psychiatrists that we spoke with
just yesterday who were gung-ho about
this.
>> So I think there are providers out
there. they just may not necessarily all
uh be at the forefront at the moment but
we need to work on that and we need to
do that. The other part and this is the
portion that uh you know and again I've
said this many a time is
>> part of the reason for launching this
and doing this in this current time
frame is that if there are issues if we
see there are blockages if we see this
doesn't is isn't implementing well or we
have problems we can then make those
adjustments and those changes. So please
keep that on in mind. um we just are
trying to ensure that it does stay as a
medical issue. We understand uh the same
arguments as far as the DEA licenses
have come up as I mentioned with regard
to cannabis. We've seen exactly how
that's worked out as far as those
recommendations over time and it does
take a lot of effort and a lot of
education but that's a part of what
we're ready and willing to do.
>> Yeah. Beautiful. Thank you.
>> So, uh Katherine, go on ahead, please.
Oh, your mic, Katherine.
What may be going on?
>> Can you hear me?
>> There you go.
>> Okay, awesome. It's just taking a long
time to unmute. Okay. Um, so I just need
clarification because I think something
significantly did change then. So
practitioners will not be able to
qualify patients with a diagnosis is
what I'm hearing. Um, and if that is the
case, I'm really concerned about uh
practicum. Like I'm really concerned
that it's going to we're not going to be
able to get people through practicum
till January or February. I was hoping
we would be able to get some practicums
out sooner. Um I think it's gonna I I
agree with Lita. I think it's going to
be um it's going to drag the program out
pretty significantly. So I just want to
chime in with that. And then just please
do clarify that yes practitioners will
not be able to diagnose then.
>> That is correct Katherine. you know um I
mean and again the other the option
would be is even if a practitioner has
so for example a licensed social worker
who has uh diagnosed somebody with PTSD
but that patient would still then need
to get that medical clearance that
diagnostic clinician to go through and
do that approval on it. Um so that is a
possibility and actually especially
where um they um you know where
practitioners are working together that
can actually help with that and that's a
part of that buildup. Um it it may take
a little longer than that time frame.
Again the December time frame is just to
see the first patient. It does not
necessarily mean that everything will be
in place as far as all the different
aspects of the program. Um, and so it
may take a little bit of time for the
rest of that to fall in. But if you
recall, our original deadline and goal
was December of 2027. I feel that with
these here, even with some of these
concerns, that we will be able to have a
very robust program by December of 27.
But we do hear you and we're going to be
monitoring that. So, uh, and then Rob
Yeah. Hi, Lita. I just wanted to address
some of your concerns and and I think
one, yes, there's a shortage of
providers in New Mexico. We can't fix
that right now. So, that's beyond the
ability of our program. Um, second, when
we thought about the diagnostic
clinician, we really thought about this.
And so, if you look at the educational
requirements for a diagnostic clinician,
they are not ownorous. The bar is low
here. We want these people simply to be
aware of what psilocybin therapy is. So
the bar is not high. Anybody can become
any physician, any nurse practitioner
etc. can become a diagnostic clinician
with a minimum of effort. So we really
thought about that bottleneck and try to
eliminate it. In third, you are correct
about the fear. The fear we can only
change through education. Um, and
remember the diagnostic clinician is not
prescribing psilocybin. They're simply
saying, "Yeah, hey, you know what? This
may be this may be a therapy you could
think about." Um, I would be happy to
say that and that's not going to
endanger my DEA lessons. Thank you.
Okay, any other questions?
Okay, so the next section
uh is uh and I'm actually putting two up
because they're pretty short on this is
the appeal process and disciplinary uh
disciplinary actions. So of course if
any application at any time is denied um
then there will be a similar appeal
process that we have currently in both
the production and laboratory processes
which is essentially that there would be
an administrative review and a final
determination again after that review.
And so that total process would be 45
days. Um that does involve review by an
administrative review committee to see
were the correct processes on part of
the department done and followed. um was
the application actually denied
inappropriately or incorrectly and so
going through that process. And then
disciplinary actions of course would be
um if again and we mentioned it in some
of the other parts where if someone for
example has uh expressed falsehood on an
application or um you know misled or
actually even engaged in um uh
sorry in unprofessional behavior those
sort of things. And then the department
would of course after an investigation
would not issue a notice of disciplinary
pardon me everybody. Can you tell it's
been an hour and a half of talking so my
apologies.
Uh the department would issue that
notice of disciplinary action and they
would be able to request a hearing and
that hearing would be overseen by a
hearing officer and of course they can
grant continuances if needed for
reasons. Um and then hearing officer
will submit a final written
recommendation within 30 calendar days
after the hearing. Um and then the
secretary would issue a final decision.
So those are things for example if an
educational uh program um violated you
know they stopped using their curriculum
didn't submit uh an updated version and
the department said hey you need to
submit this and it needs to be reviewed.
That would be an example of a notice of
disciplinary action. Um, and if they
appealed that, and by the way, in those
kinds of cases, people usually have or
organizations have 30 days or so to be
able to actually resolve it. But if they
did not, then that's where the actions
would come in. I hope I explained that
well. My apologies if it didn't come
across clearly.
But any questions? I thought I saw
something up a moment ago.
Was it in the chat or?
>> No, I just I thought I just as I was
splitting between the two windows, I
just must have missed it. That's okay.
>> That hand went Chris had his hand went
back down.
>> Oh, okay.
Chris, did you want to speak? Did you
have a question or a comment?
Uh Chris, you had had your hand up
earlier, so why don't you go first?
>> Yeah, my mic was my mic was muted. Oh,
>> so I guess I I was just wanting to
comment on something that uh Dr.
Truckner was talking about which is if
if the doctor is just
I guess saying that this might be a
treatment that you want. He's not
actually providing a prescription
and he's just he's doing medical
clearance at that point. If something
goes wrong physically, is it is it li
does liability come back on the doctor?
Um
yeah, I guess that's my question. Mhm.
>> So the doctor's not actually doing the
treatments themselves because that then
moves on to the practitioners and the
healing centers.
>> So we're essentially creating an extra
step for the patient to see somebody who
doesn't take on any responsibility for
the outcome
is what I'm hearing.
No, they still have to have done the
appropriate evaluations and ensure that
they're doing that medical clearance.
Those are the aspects that they are
taking responsibility for, not the
treatment itself.
>> So, physically, if something goes wrong,
then the doctor would be held
responsible for that.
>> Something was missed in a medical
clearance.
>> Sorry, Chris. I'm going to let Rob go
ahead and answer.
>> Yeah, Chris, I mean, first of all, we
can be sued for anything any time, but
yes, we will be medically liable. We are
not going to avoid liability here. Um, I
have to clear the patient if he's got
heart disease, if he's got diabetes. I
I'm going to stick my neck out as far as
saying yes, I have responsibility to
ensure this patient has a reasonable
chance to undergo psilocybin therapy
successfully without harm. That is
that's not my DEA license. That's just
me being a physician. Um so the DEA
license has nothing to do with my
responsibilities
um to to to clear this patient safely.
Does that answer your question?
Yeah, I think so. And I,
[clears throat] you know, I'm a little
frustrated with this rule. Like I think
Colorado and Oregon are both showing
that this, you know, medical screening
can be done at a much lower level than
physicians. I think this is going to
create a huge bottleneck and and if it
doesn't really like I think you're
minimizing the fear level here like when
you're saying that that doctors are
not
going to be held accountable for
anything then what are they what are
they doing? I I just I'm struggling with
it. So,
>> well Chris, we are being held
accountable. um we're always held
accountable and that's part of my job.
Um and and I think the other thing, the
reason I don't sleep at night is because
the patients we're going to be treating
are sick patients, right? They have
significant medical problems and
psychological problems. And this is a
much higher risk pool than Colorado and
Oregon overall. So yeah, I don't sleep
at night. Um yeah, there's a lot of
reasons I worry about this.
I'm not sure I agree that we have
different population base here that
we're working with, but I will uh go
ahead and relinquish my time to
Heneifeha.
>> Okay. Thank you, Chris. And actually uh
Lita was next, but we will uh go in
order at this point. So, uh Lita, go on
ahead.
>> Thank you so much for this conversation.
Um my question is regarding the eight
hours of training for the diagnostic
clinician. Is that provided by the state
um or does the clinician have to find um
you know a training program to do that
or how how are you guys envisioning
that?
>> Thank you Lita. Uh that would actually
be the educational programs would need
to provide that. Um and but again we
will be having that information for the
approved programs will be listed on the
department site.
>> Understood. Thank you so much.
>> Thank you. Okay Greg,
>> uh quite briefly um confirm
[clears throat] if I understand this
correctly. clinician would be
responsible for the accuracy of their
assessment and if applicable diagnosis
not so much for the efficacy of the
treatment itself. Is that
>> the right designation?
>> Yes, that is correct. Greg,
>> okay, that that calms my spirit on that
need for their accountability. It's like
broken arm, broken arm, not broken leg.
>> Right.
Exactly. Thank you, Greg.
Uh, Hanifeha.
[snorts]
>> Hey. Um, enjoying the conversation. And
also, I think maybe Greg just answered
my question because it sounds like the
diagnosing clinician is actually holding
two roles. They're confirming and or
assessing if a client or patient has one
of the conditions
and then they're also doing the medical
screening prior to saying that the
patient can access the psilocybin
program. Is that correct?
>> Correct, Teneifa. So for example looking
at things like are they on medications
that might be problematic or do they
have other conditions or
counterindications
uh for doing this treatment. Um does
that make sense?
>> Yes. But if if the client already is
diagnosed say for PTS and they already
have the diagnosis, they're already have
gone through therapy or receiving other
treatments, can they just bring you know
the documentation from the person who
diagnosed them to this other person to
do the medical clearing?
>> So that would be up to the that
individual provider. Um and but the the
other aspect to remember is people's
condition changes over time and so
somebody may have gotten a diagnosis
five six years ago and so um they still
are probably going to want to evaluate.
However, if for example someone just had
received the diagnosis and um you know
um say uh it's a situation where the
provider uh had diagnosed them was still
was working with them and then either
whether they were afraid to uh refer
them into the program or moved out of
state and the patient didn't really have
contact but they have the records they
could then go to someone else and say
another provider and say look I just got
diagnosed two months ago here are the
records. that provider would still want
to do their due diligence, but that
would actually help them in that.
>> Thank you. And a little on the
tangential level is, you know, curious
to know like what's the timeline for the
very much needed
public education and awareness to
medical professionals to get them
interested in becoming one of these
diagnosing clinicians so we can bump the
numbers up and they have time to get
their their certificate.
Well, we've already been doing it in
some of our uh other educational
programs and talking about the program
and moving it forward. But, uh once once
the regulations really get moving
forward and the program uh is on a
little bit more of the implementation
path um at that point we will be ramping
up those kinds of uh educational
portions.
>> Wonderful.
>> But there's not much.
>> Yeah. Not an exact timeline though,
Hanifeha. But, you know, that's, you
know, we're not saying, we're not
looking at it as being, oh, we're not
going to start that until January.
That's going to be here over the next
couple of months.
>> Gotcha. Okay. Thanks.
>> No, thank you. Oh, uh, Rob.
>> Yeah, Hanifeh, I just wanted to jump in.
Um I I think your scenario is plausible
if some if a patient went to let's say a
psychiatrist
um who can diagnose and has a controlled
substance number and they're diagnosed
with PTSD but they're not comfortable
with the hypoglycemia the patient has
because of their di diabetes and they
don't want to clear that then they could
send that to me as a diagnosing
clinician. you know, if a psychiatrist
tells me someone has PTSD, I'm going to
believe them. Um, especially within that
reasonable time period, and then I'm
going to work on doing the medical
clearance to be sure it's safe for that
patient to undergo the therapy. Thank
you.
>> Okay. and James,
>> Tom, Robert, and everybody, you know,
just to echo Chris a little bit more
because it is kind of one of those
things that we need to work out and
discuss and and figure out. A lot of
this, you know, and in in our
subcommittees, we're talking about the
bottleneck, right? And some of this
bottleneck effect could be co caused
due to the fact that
providers don't want to opt in. That's
that's that's the theme, right? But
we've known that it could be because of
the lack of re of of access to a program
and and that's going to be big cost of
course, you know, and some of these
other things that we think about. But
really when we're we're talking about
this guys is
it creates a bottleneck when you have
these the facilitators are trained
individuals and and they're very
educated. They're going to be they're
going to be educated both didactically
and you know practicumly. So they're
going to have all this the tools that
they need through these programs. Okay,
if you think about it, you know, if they
if they graduate from a program, they're
going to have all the tools necessary to
to start what they they want to do. And
so with that, that causes a bottleneck
though. And so if if we don't allow and
and we're trying to figure it all out
and I understand that of of who's going
to get liability and who's not and we
you know we're in a very let's just say
it you know latigious state you know you
know that I know that everybody knows
that and so with that you know
facilitators need to have some options
here for some of these things. It's been
proven already. So the groundwork's
already been set. So that's that you can
use that. And so these facilitators need
to me and I'm with Chris that we need to
have a little bit more of this
responsibility back to the facilitator
due to access and so that we can get the
these people through their sessions, get
the data that we need to prove this
program and and instead of you know
having at the end of the day in a year
we have let's say a couple hundred
people in a safe manner. Of course,
maybe if you guys if we all rethink
about this some about a facilitator
having some of these screening processes
to limit
some of the bottlenecking. It's just a
thought because then we would definitely
allow and again it's already been preset
pre-approved pre done in two states
already. Um it's just a thought again
about some of this you know so we don't
prevent this bottleneck effect. Um thank
you so much.
Thank you, James.
Okay. And Ann uh you just put in the
chat about will there be uh them
available when the program starts.
That's a part of why we are doing these
rules now so that there will be uh the
situation with um uh where individuals
will be able to receive the training
through some of the educational programs
to be able to do that but also um that
is a part of the reciprocity aspects of
it.
So thank you with regard to that and and
as mentioned we just even yesterday
spoke with two psychiatrists for example
who are ready and willing to do so. So
thank you uh Heneifea go ahead.
>> Thank you. I I just wanted to just share
a perspective you know I'm a psilocybin
facilitator and I do a lot of work with
retreats and so within the retreat model
there is a medical screener you know and
so when people apply to come on the
retreat they have to pass the medical
clearance and then they become a part of
a cohort. Now, as a facilitator, where I
do interject into like their care model
um and their treatment, if you will, is
like we talk, I look at all of their
medical records. I talk to them and have
a conversation and check in and
particularly on the day of the medicine,
but then we are making decisions around
what dosage they'll start at. And so I'm
curious where the dosage recommendation
and responsibility will come into regard
with with this particular setup.
>> Thank you, Heneifeha. And that actually
should be a part of what the care team
actually determines and that's a part of
what's been discussed within the best
practices uh in the dosage and
administration
uh section. But again, those are about
guidelines as far as that aspect and not
something that is part of the rule. I
hope that helps.
>> That makes sense. Thank you.
>> And and part of the way I say that is
you don't want to put in a rule, for
example, that someone needs to take, you
know, 20 grams, 20 milligrams, you know,
etc. You don't want to have that sort of
thing in a rule that becomes then we're
legislating.
[laughter]
>> It was less of the amount, but like who
who determines that? So it's very
important to me that the facilitators
determine that and that's the diagnosing
kind of clearance person. Okay. Thanks.
>> Yeah. And that should be a part of that
what the care team determines. Yes.
>> Thank you. Um and then I I just want to
be we only have a few minutes left. So
Katherine um I'll go to you in just a
moment but we do have just uh the next
set is really just about the
requirements for the healing center. And
I would like to uh be able to show that.
Are people okay with staying a few
minutes later?
We And by the way, I just let everybody
know we're pretty close to the end on
this.
I'm seeing thumbs up. So, okay,
Katherine, go ahead.
Yes. So, thank you for answering my
question, but I uh in the chat, but I
think I still have questions about it.
So are you saying that a healing so a
healing center um that has a practicum
can't have clients at that center do
they have to work with a he with so a
training I'm sorry
>> that's okay let me
>> I'll see if I can do this so a training
program itself doesn't necessarily have
to operate a healing center healing
centers are separate
>> a training center could operate a
healing center so that would be fine
>> can a healing center be a training
center? Like can they can they both the
same place
>> if they apply and they you know have met
the requirements of a training center?
Absolutely.
>> So then they would have to apply to
both. They would have to apply to be
both.
>> There isn't a healing center option.
>> Correct. You would just apply under both
those requirements in order to be able
to do to serve dual purpose.
>> Okay.
Does that make sense? And and you're
going to see here in the requirements
for the healing center, it's not going
to be all that much different for what
is needed
>> for that. So,
>> it just sounds like it's going to be
more costly and uh because you know to
for a I think like for me I think I can
have a training center where I can uh
have clients come to the training center
but now I'm hearing I have to be a
healing center too. So, I'm going to
have to do both which is probably going
to cost a lot. So,
>> yeah. I I think when you see it won't
because again the only difference there
is you submitting the application okay
to the department and meeting the
requirements okay
>> for that you'd still have to meet the
requirements either way if you're seeing
patient so
>> sure of course but remember there's no
application fee to the department
>> I didn't know that that makes a huge
difference thank you very much yeah
>> okay yeah and I mean you could think of
it this way Katherine is if you're
planning on doing both What you're
really looking at is trying to get
endorsements for both a training center
and a healing center.
Okay. Um Chris, go ahead.
Um, I can't remember where I saw it in
here, but there was mention of a mobile
training or a mobile uh treatment unit
type of uh possibility. And how would
they work into healing center
requirements or would they fall into
like another approved location type of
rule?
>> You know, Chris, we're about to go into
that section. So, if you'll hold a pin
on that, uh, I think we might be able to
answer that.
Okay, thank you. Okay, so we'll again
just in the uh
as far as from a time perspective, we'll
move forward. Oh, and um I do see um we
had announced it in the meeting the
education or I'm sorry the equity
meeting on Tuesday and I alluded to it
earlier um but uh because we are just
focused on this um the just so everybody
knows um and there's an announcement
that is going out but um the rule for
the propagation and for laboratories was
uh promulgated um this week on Tuesday
and so that is out there that is ready.
It's uh people can review it, can read
it. Um and it is uh Jorge put it in the
chat just before I posted the healing
center requirements. So it is a huge
step forward. Um and and again I do want
to actually remind everybody that as we
go through for portions with regard to
definitions, as we move through with the
rules, the different sets we're doing,
we are amending them. So for example,
one great example was uh when we first
started with the rule, everybody was
telling us use the term guide and then
of course there was some concern with
that and that we should switch it over
to facilitator. So we have that in this
next set of rules. So it will change
that. Um and uh some other changes with
regard to that as well. Um so
uh and with that let me go on ahead. So
here are this healing center
requirements. So again the application
for this would be similar to the other
processes. They would be submitted in
the same way and online. So the healing
center requirements are they must submit
it through the electronic system. The
name of the business or organizational
chart again their proof of registration
with secretary of state and New Mexico
tax and rent. Uh any applicable New
Mexico City county business licenses,
their certificate of occupation for
locations utilized in New Mexico. and
then additional documents as the
department may reasonably request to
ensure compliance with local laws,
regulations, etc. Uh listing contact
information for owners or if member if
it's a board of directors, the board of
directors. Primary contact information
including name, address, phone, and
email. Maintain a list of all permitted
individuals who will be utilizing or
will utilize uh the location. Plans for
record retention and confidentiality.
Plans for secured storage for
medication. Any wastage. Plans for
wastage of any unused medication. Safety
and emergency response plan. Documented
policies and procedures for possession
and storage of firearms or other weapons
safely on the approved location
premises. Um, by the way, that policy
can be no weapons or firearms or it
could be um uh could be um uh could be
that they are allowed. That would be up
to the location. Plans demonstrating
confidentiality of patients will be
maintained within the approved location.
Plans for transparency and disclosure of
fees. Outline of complaint and grievance
process procedures for patients. consent
for contact information and websites to
be listed publicly on the department
website if approved. And for those
conducting sessions in natural
environments, they would need to also
include permission to utilize the
property, detailed description of the
outdoor administration area, including
identification of safe entrances and
exits and verification the area is free
of hazards. an emergency safety and
response plan and two individuals
present who are not receiving treatment
and who have either a wilderness first
aid or first responder certification.
And then of course the plan for adverse
health event response and reporting.
Any questions on this?
Chris, go ahead.
Um I guess so my question is on the
maintain a list of all permitted
individuals who will be utilizing the
space. So would would multi-use spaces
be
uh available? Would we be able to use
like a yoga studio or something like
that?
>> Yes. And Chris, what this is just
referring to is which you know
practitioners, facilitators are doing
that. So if you had, for example, you
were doing a yoga studio on Monday,
Tuesday and doing psilocybin treatment
the other days of the week, um the if
you have an instructor for the yoga
studio, they don't need to be listed on
it. Um this is really just it's the
permits for uh for the and the
certifications for the providers that
are going to be doing treatments.
>> And I guess this makes what brings up
one more question for me. If we have
volunteer facilitators, are they going
to need to be permitted?
>> Yes. But the uh you also can have
individuals who are doing other things
outside the facilitation realm who do
not need to be permitted.
>> Okay.
>> For example, if you have someone who's
just helping with ensuring there's food,
water, you know, things like that, that
that's a staff member or a volunteer,
that's not a permitted position or role.
But those people would be allowed in in
journey spaces
>> uh with permission. Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> Absolutely. Great question.
>> Okay. And then um the next set is the
other approved locations.
Um
put that on here in the chat. So uh that
it would include the potential for a
patient's residence or other temporary
location uh if it is not possible for
the patient to physically go to a
healing center for reasons of medical
necessity. All items must be submitted
through the electronic system again. So
list of the permitted individuals
utilizing it. Um plan for secure
transportation and if necessary storage
of medication plans for
wastage of any unused medication.
um a safety and emergency response plan.
Uh again, plan for storage of firearms
or weapons and plans demonstrating
confidentiality of patients
and a description of why the location is
appropriate for the treatment sessions.
Okay. And uh the next part is uh the
healing center and other approved
locations.
Uh thank you Jessica. The question is
who decides the medical necessity? Uh
again that can be um uh that actually
can be uh the care team. Um so it should
be the diagnostic clinician but it can
be done in um in conjunction with the
practitioner as well.
Great question on that and we'll make
sure to clarify that.
So, the healing center and other
approved location responsibilities,
uh, the products may only be consumed in
an approved location. Only patients and
certified individuals may be present
during a patient treatment unless each
patient gives prior written consent for
other individuals except in emergency
response situations.
Um,
a permittee must maintain a copy of the
daily log of activities related to
psilocybin in the department designated
electronic reporting system. May not
promote unregulated cultivation and
processing of psilocybin products and
may not sell unregulated psilocybin
products and provide uh required
information to the department upon
request and in the form and manner uh
requested by the department. And the
healing center must display a copy of
their identifi their certification
issued by the department and information
regarding safe transportation after an
administration session.
And the next section is about the center
uh safety and emergency plan.
Oh Chris, go ahead.
So, I guess I missed it if you talked
about how a
like a mobile
um service team might
uh be able to operate in rural areas or
something like that.
>> Oh, you know what? I'm sorry, Chris.
Thank you for catching that. We did have
um
you know what it looks like that line is
not in here. I will find that and we
will add that back on in. It did have
that for mobile units as well. You were
correct in having seen it at one point.
Um I will make sure that gets added back
in.
>> Okay. So that's going to be part of the
>> healing or other approved location
requirements.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Okay. And will there be specific rules
around how they need to what they need
to do to set those up?
>> Uh the same items here that we have in
there. It's just that line got deleted
or not copied over. So thank you.
>> Excellent. I just want to
try to make sure that we're being
responsive and able to
>> to serve rural areas.
>> No, no, completely agree with you and we
did have it. Like I said, it just uh
again, we're working from uh [laughter]
well, [snorts] we'll just say that it
takes a lot to go through and sometimes
we make mistakes as we've always said.
So, that's part of why we do this
because we want to ensure that we're
catching those items. So, thank you,
Chris.
Uh and I'm sorry, where were we? Uh
service center plan, emergency plan.
There we go.
Uh and then basically on this it's that
every location shall maintain a safety
and emergency plan. So documenting
procedures for evacuation, relocating
patients if something becomes unsafe. Uh
if there's a medical or other emergency,
uh if there's how to address disruptive
conduct or patient reactions that do not
require or rise to the level of
requiring an emergency response and um
documenting procedures for patients who
attempt to leave a treatment session
against medical advice. Um and really in
this we medical advice we mean for
everything you know for practitioners
anybody who is there uh and then provide
the emergency and safety plan to all
individuals utilizing the location and
then if the procedures are needing to be
utilized. So say for example there is an
emergency it will be documented and that
will include if the plan was adhered to
or if there were deviations what might
be changed in the future to ensure
safety of the individuals.
Okay. And I'm going to combine the next
two portions.
Oh, Greg, sorry. I just saw that you're
you had your hand up. Go ahead.
>> Just really quick. And it may end up in
a different part of the ruling or maybe
it's a Yeah, it should be in a rule
somewhere. Um, how are we handling
reporting those types of situations?
Or is that covered here or somewhere?
>> That's just it's through the uh online
reporting system.
>> Oh, okay. Everything goes through the
same same portal. Thank you.
>> Correct. Yeah. No, great question. Thank
you, Greg.
>> So, as I Oh, sorry. As so I'm sorry. So,
um so it would be like an incident
reporting on online. Okay.
>> Right. Right. Um and uh so storage uh
all psilocybin products stored at an
approved location must be kept in a lock
area. must be either an area enclosed on
all sides with permanent walls and
secured with at a minimum a properly
installed steel door with a steel frame
and commercial gradede non-residential
lock or a locked safe. And then of
course products that require
refrigeration may be stored within a
locked refrigerator or freezer.
Any questions on that?
Okay. And then adverse health reporting.
Um and again this would be online for
the department. Um and so uh any adverse
health event associated with psilocybin
services please to be reported no later
than within two business days um through
the designated system and healing
centers must maintain records of the
adverse health health event reports in
accordance with the rules. They must
include the patient record number, any
participant reaction requiring medical
attention and any incident requiring
emergency response and other incidences
which have a negative impact on a
patient.
Uh and then the next set is complaint
complaint reporting.
Oh, and Heneife you have a question in
there. Um that is something we are not
putting in the rule at this time,
but definitely would um require uh you
know, it would be a very good idea for
them to have insurance on that.
>> Oh, Greg, you have your hand up. Go
ahead.
>> Yeah, you're getting me at the end here.
Um just I would recommend including
product ID.
>> Oh, thank you.
Okay. And then so the next set is
complaint reporting. Patients or staff
uh may lodge a complaint with the
department. The complaint should be in
writing and include name and contact
information for the complaint and which
will remain confidential. the nature of
the complaint and any individuals who
may be involved and the department may
request additional information for
investigation purposes. Um we will also
have that online but of course as with
anything there are certain things people
want to do through um through mail as
far as for complaints. So that would
also be an option. And then the healing
centers and approved locations must take
adequate measures um to uh make the
instructions or guidance available
related to how to file the complaint
with the department
uh or other relevant state entities and
how to report an adverse health event.
And that's the end of it.
>> Dominic, thank you.
And we do know that there are some
concerns, you know, and and I know that
that's, you know, we've discussed those.
Um I know some of the people have had to
leave. Um we will be bringing this with
these changes to the board meeting
tomorrow. Um and [snorts] uh to discuss
them, but you know, as we continue
talking about it, you know, we're not at
the rule hearing yet, but even with the
rule hearing there things can change.
You know, none of this is set in stone.
And even after the rule hearing and even
after promulgation, if there are issues,
if there are concerns, if things do
indeed end up creating the bottlenecks
that people are talking about and
concerned about, we can still change
that. We want to get the program started
up here in December, but as our original
goal was December of 27, if we need to
make changes in between to alleviate
those issues, we will do so. Um, a lot
of this has been, as I've mentioned,
with conversations [snorts] with lots of
different people, entities, both
locally, nationally, community oriented,
otherwise. Uh, none of this has been
done in a vacuum. Um, and and I'll tell
you the amount of conflicting
information from different organizations
or people, the conflicting fears, the
conflicting issues, um, there's a lot
and we share many of them. And our goal
is in the end to have the best program.
As I've said many times before, will
there be mistakes? Will be there there
be things that need to change?
Absolutely. And we recognize that. We
have done that with other programs in
the past. This is a very different
program and a very different statute
than the other states, Colorado and
Oregon currently have. So there are
different considerations sometimes that
go there. So it's not always and and we
have [clears throat] looked at where can
we import um some of those ideas and
also some of the issues and concerns but
um so please be patient with us just
because we get things started here in
December does not mean that's the end
and it doesn't mean things won't change
down the road. Um so I I know we're over
by about 15 minutes and I really
appreciate everyone being here. I do see
James has his hand on up. So, I'd like
>> one last one last customer here.
>> Yeah. So, uh James, go on ahead. And
then, um the next part we'll need to do,
Brenda, is just to set the next date.
>> So, James,
>> real quick, uh just real one more
question on this document. Is there an
echoing of a quality review process? I
just didn't know when I'm when I read it
over and over again a couple times. it.
You know, I don't know if that needs to
fit in here anywhere with the centers or
I just the difference between the two
programs is that we don't have a quality
review process really in the other
programs and and I just didn't know if
there needed to be something adv
advocated towards that. Thank you.
That's all.
>> Thank you, James. That's actually a
great question. And that's actually that
very concern for example is one of the
reasons why the we had the third party
evaluator portion in the curriculum for
the educational programs to have that
kind of quality review that quality uh
portion on it. But the other side of
that is that uh that is a part of what
the department will be doing. That's why
the department has the ability to go in
to conduct those compliance visits to be
able to go in. That's why there's the
portion about, you know, notices of
contemplated action in case something is
found outside the regulations or things
aren't being done correctly or
appropriately. So, that is a part of uh
that aspect and I hope that helps.
>> And Dom, just real quick on that, I I
totally understand the DO's side coming
in on the regulatory side, but really
there needs to be an internal center
side. there needs to be something
internally that these people's programs
have something that they need to
specifically re be reviewing and their
own program per se. Thank you.
>> Great. Thank you, James. I appreciate
that. And yes, they should have that,
but that's not necessarily something
that is a regulatory issue, but yes,
they should absolutely do that.
>> Well, I think that wraps it up, huh?
Yeah.
>> Um so I want to thank everyone. This was
um great. Your participation
um is very very important to this
program and I just want to say all of
your questions were just on point.
Really great questions and this helps us
shape what we need to do and make this a
great program. So I want to thank
everybody's participation in this. Can't
do it without you.
>> I agree. And so, um, Brenda, uh, next
date,
>> uh, what, um, Fridays are good. Uh, what
what do you have open?
>> Uh, we are, uh, our normal one would,
oh, well, I would say normally we would
be on Friday the 10th if we went two
weeks from now, but both research and
>> uh, end of life are uh,
>> both have meetings scheduled on that
day. So, let me take a quick look here.
Um,
uh,
would Friday the 17th work for people?
>> Yes, Friday the 17th.
>> Yes. And the usual one to three.
>> Perfect.
>> Okay. Well, we will get that um
scheduled and out there. And really
thank you to everybody. I know a lot of
people unfortunately had to leave, but
you know, considering how long the
document was and we didn't really start
reviewing it until about 20 after one,
we actually got through it in two hours.
So with a lot of really great
conversation and points. So I'm very
appreciative of that.
Okay, Brenda, unless you have anything
else, thank you to everybody.
>> That's it. Thank you everyone and have a
great week. And um geez, we're getting
on the 4th of July here. So we do have a
a do meeting tomorrow, right? From 9 to
11.
>> Yes, the board the board meeting. So
we'll be there tomorrow. So thank you
again everyone of you. Thank you.
>> Thank you everyone.